what are border carbon adjustments bcas
and why are countries interested in
implementing them climate change
mitigation policies such as carbon
pricing are becoming increasingly
ambitious in countries around the world
as they aim to curb their greenhouse gas
emissions ghgs in 2024 close to a
quarter of global emissions will be
covered by an explicit carbon price and
the trend is clear more will be covered
going forward but efforts to price
carbon domestically can result in
shifting economic activity and therefore
shifting ghg emissions to other
jurisdictions with less ambitious
climate policies this is called carbon
leakage the activities most vulnerable
to carbon leakage are emissions
intensive trade exposed sectors such as
steel cement and
aluminum to prevent carbon leakage many
countries are considering establishing
border carbon adjustments or bcas these
are a mechanism that charges Imports at
the border as if they had been produced
under the domestic carbon pricing regime
the European Union has had a be CA says
2023 the carbon border adjustment
mechanism or cound the United Kingdom
will likely have one by 2027 other
economies are exploring options
including Australia Canada Chinese type
and the United States bcas are driven by
a concern for leakage and the risk of
leakage in turn is driven by carbon
pricing which more and more countries
are adopting the upshot is more and more
countries will consider adopting bcas
BCA regimes are not a single instrument
they're more like a decision tree at
many points in their elaboration there
are design choices that can Branch the
final regime out into different
directions the final shape of the regime
can look very different depending on
these choices to better understand the
possibilities let's take a look at six
of the most fundamental choices Decision
One Trade scope here the question is
will the BCA assess a levy on Imports
only or will exports also be covered the
regime could rebate the cost of carbon
at the point of export the way it's done
for a value added tax ta doing so would
be good for BCA covered firms that have
a lot of exports and would prevent the
loss of their global market share but
removing the carbon price from those
goods reduces the incentives that a
carbon price is supposed to transmit as
well export rebates may be illegal Under
World Trade Organization rules there's a
higher chance of this if the domestic
carbon pricing regime is a regulation
like an emissions trading scheme but
even a carbon tax is not a sure bet
decision two exemptions will the BCA
exempt any States from coverage we could
imagine exempting least developed
countries for example because they've
done so little to contribute to climate
change or countries with strong climate
policies but that would involve a
unilateral determination of how poor a
country should be or how ambitious they
should be in implementing climate
policies in order to Merit that
exemption that's a controversial
Prospect as well different treatment of
some WTO members May violate the wto's
most favored nation principle especially
if not all developing countries would
fall under such an exemption decision
three scope of emissions what ghg
emissions will be covered a bcas will
normally cover all of the emissions that
occur within the facility producing a
good that's the so-called direct
emissions but should they also cover
emissions bound up in any purchased
electricity steam or heat not doing so
disadvantages foreign producers with
clean electricity supplies how about the
emissions bound up in input Goods like
the basic steel that's used to produce
steel pipes or from transporting the
goods to Market decision four carbon
accounting when a good arrives at the
border how will a BCA regime estimate
its embedded carbon the regime could
demand actual data and that's a costly
demand to comply with but it's fair or
it could use default values for the ght
intensity of production and these could
range anywhere from generous assumptions
to punitive ones like the worst
available technology defaults are much
simpler to comply with but they can be
unfair to clean producers and to
generous to ghg intense
producers decision five credit for
foreign
action will the Border charge be lowered
to reflect foreign climate actions if
the foreign producer has paid a carbon
price already for example to charge
another at the border amounts to double
pricing so there should probably be
credit but it's not clear what amounts
to a carbon price does it have to be an
economy-wide carbon price or could it be
a carbon price just for the exports of
certain Goods be Beyond explicit carbon
prices what about costly climate
regulations should there be credit for
those one of the key challenges is that
in principle if a BCA regime is
crediting for non-price based climate
policies in the country of export it
should also be raising the Border charge
to account for domestic non-price based
climate policies in the country of
import and this would be
controversial decision six use of
revenues what happens to the funds that
are collected at the border should they
go back to the affected exporters or
their host countries should they be used
to help domestic firms decarbonize
should they be kept as General Revenue
sending the money back would be a strong
signal that the regime was not about
protecting domestic producers and would
be a way to compensate for the costs of
compliance that are faced by affected
firms the need for international
cooperation bcas are a new instrument
there hasn't been time yet to forge
agreement on how to make them work as a
piece of the complex puzzle that is
international economic and environmental
governance there are at least three
reasons why International agreement and
cooperation are urgently
needed one a proliferation of many bcas
might mean that exporters would have to
comply with many different requirements
for measurement reporting and
verification in different markets that
would be a nightmare scenario especially
for smaller developing country producers
a spaghetti bowl of conflicting
duplicative and trade restrictive
requirements two even the best designed
bcas will impose costs on foreign
producers linked to to the creation of
new internal carbon accounting regimes
to reporting to certification of their
data again exporters from small and
developing countries will be the most
burdened there's a need then to create
greater interoperability among BCA
regimes to support the most effective
producers in
complying three the answers to the
design questions we discussed could lean
anywhere in the final regime Landing
along a spectrum from genuine
Environmental Protection to the unfair
protection of domestic producers
International cooperation would work to
identify best practices could guide
domestic policy makers and hold them
accountable to an internationally agreed
standard that would move the final
result closer to Environmental
Protection